Finding Aid for Fred M. Davenport papers, 1955-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fred M. Davenport papers 1955-1972
Davenport, Fred M. (Fred Marshall), 1914-1982.
15 linear feet
85130 Aa 2
Professor of epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of Michigan, director of the Commission on Influenza, U. S. Armed Forces Epidemiological Board. Professional files concerning commission work and as chairman of the U. S. Viral Disease Panel.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. Fred M. Davenport (donor no. 4866 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Fred M. Davenport was born in Scranton, Penn., on Nov. 30, 1914. He received his undergraduate degree in 1936 and his medical degree in 1940 at Columbia University. He joined the Army Medical Corps as a malariologist during World War II, and from 1942 to 1946 saw service in Central America, Australia, New Guinea, the Philippines, Okinawa and Japan. In 1947 Davenport was awarded a National Research Council Fellowship in virus diseases, enabling him to spend two additional years of postdoctoral training at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, where he worked under Dr. F.L. Horsfall on serological research with influenza viruses.
Davenport came to the University of Michigan School of Public Health in 1949 as a research associate in epidemiology. Here he collaborated with Dr. Thomas Francis Jr., in research on virology and the epidemiology of influenza. In 1951 he received an additional appointment in the U-M Medical School's internal medicine department. He was promoted to professor of epidemiology in 1958 and professor of internal medicine in 1959. He became chairman of the department of epidemiology in 1969 upon the retirement of Dr. Francis.
Davenport's research on virus diseases and on the problem of the control and prevention of epidemic influenza earned him a significant international reputation. In 1967 he was named an honorary member of the Robert Koch Institute, Berlin, Germany. A year later he was awarded the Memorial Medal and Badge of Gamaleya by the Institute of Epidemiology and Microbiology of the Academy of Medical Sciences of the Soviet Union.
In addition, Davenport was an associate member of the Armed Forces Epidemiologic Board and served as director of its Commission on Influenza from 1955 to 1971. Between 1969 and 1973 he served as chairman of the virus diseases panel of the U.S.-Japan Cooperative Medical Science Program. He also served as a consultant to many national and international organizations, including the Food and Drug Administration and the World Health Organization.
Davenport retired from the University faculty in 1977 and was subsequently named professor emeritus of epidemiology and internal medicine. He died March 2, 1982.
This collection, only partially processed, is divided into four series: Commission on Influenza; Armed Forces Epidemiological Board; U.S. Viral Disease Panel; and Department of Epidemiology, University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Epidemiology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; Public health--United States.; United States. Armed Forces Epidemiological Board.
- Commission on Influenza
  - July 1955-June 1957 (Box 1)
  - July 1957-June 1958 (Box 2)
  - July 1958-December 1959 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 6)
- Armed Forces Epidemiological Board
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Board meetings, 1961-1972
    - 1961-1968 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1968 (Box 7)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 9)
  - Memoranda (Box 8)
  - Viral Infections (Box 8)
  - Member Correspondence (Box 8)
  - Commission Meetings (Box 8)
  - Acute respiratory disease (Box 9)
  - Cutaneous diseases (Box 9)
  - Enteric infections (Box 10)
  - Environmental health (Box 10)
  - Epidemiological survey (Box 10)
  - Immunization (Box 10)
  - Malaria (Box 10)
  - Military accidents (Box 10)
  - Parasitic diseases (Box 10)
  - Rickettsial diseases (Box 10)
  - Streptococcal diseases (Box 10)
- U.S. Viral Disease Panel
  - Member correspondence (Box 11)
  - Administrative files (Box 11)
  - Contracts (Box 11)
  - Grants (Box 12)
  - Reports (Box 12)
  - Meetings (Box 12)
  - Meetings (Box 13)
  - Conferences (Box 13)
  - Conferences (Box 14)
  - Conference on rabies, 1970 (Box 14)
- Department of Epidemiology, University of Michigan
  - Minutes of staff meetings (Box 15)
  - Annual reports (Box 15)